<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of all such fights, skirmishes, exploites, and other politike attempts which haue happened in France since the ariuall of the Duke of Parma, and the ioyning of his forces with the enemies Wherein is most truelie declared the good successe of the Kings Maiestie, and the manner of the entrenching of the said Duke with all his forces in a moore, neere vnto the castle of Brou. Trulie translated, and published according to the originall sent by the French King to his embassador heere in England.</title>
            <title>Sommaire discours au vray de ce qui est advenu en l'armée du Roy Tres-Chrestien depuis que le duc de Parme s'est ioint a celle des ennemis. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847900</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12964</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01154)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12964)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of all such fights, skirmishes, exploites, and other politike attempts which haue happened in France since the ariuall of the Duke of Parma, and the ioyning of his forces with the enemies Wherein is most truelie declared the good successe of the Kings Maiestie, and the manner of the entrenching of the said Duke with all his forces in a moore, neere vnto the castle of Brou. Trulie translated, and published according to the originall sent by the French King to his embassador heere in England.</title>
                  <title>Sommaire discours au vray de ce qui est advenu en l'armée du Roy Tres-Chrestien depuis que le duc de Parme s'est ioint a celle des ennemis. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Scarlet, dwelling at the signe of the greene Dragon in Adling street, and are to be sold by William Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1590]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Sommaire discours au vray de ce qui est advenu en l'armée du Roy Tres-Chrestien depuis que le duc de Parme s'est ioint a celle des ennemis.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12964:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12964:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE OF ALL SVCH FIGHTS, Skirmiſhes, Exploites, and other poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike attempts which haue happened in <hi>France</hi> ſince the ariuall of the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> and <hi>the ioyning of his Forces with the Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is moſt truelie declared the good ſucceſſe of the Kings Maieſtie, and the manner of the entren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the ſaid Duke with all his Forces in a Moore, neere vnto the Caſtle of</hi> Brou.</p>
            <p>Trulie tranſlated, and publiſhed according to the originall ſent by the French King to his Embaſſador heere in England.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by Thomas Scarlet, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the ſigne of the greene Dragon in Adling ſtreet, and are to be ſold by <hi>William Wright.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12964:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12964:2"/>
            <head>A true diſcourſe of all that hath happened in the moſt Chriſtian Kings Armie ſince the ariuall of the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and the ioyning of his <hi>forces with the enemie, vntill the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth daie of this preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of September.</hi> 1590.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that great and happie victorie which it pleaſed God to giue the King againſt his enemies néere to <hi>Eury</hi> the fourtéenth of March laſt paſt, he alſo vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to grant him ſuch peculiar fauour (vnto conquerors not vſuall) as therby to be no whit puffed vp either in déede or word, but contrariwiſe to growe the more gracious and tractable, as may appeare in his releaſing of a great part of the rigour of his Edicts and declarations againſt his rebellious townes &amp; ſubiects after the ſaid victory more then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Which cauſe was worth vnto him fiftene or ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene good cities &amp; townes, whereof only one held out the batterie, and all the reſt yéelded vppon friendly compoſition, and haue ſince continued moſt firme, conſtant, and reſolute in his ſeruice, as hauing tried that tranſferring themſelues from a tyranous vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation to a lawfull dominion, their ſtate was greatly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12964:3"/> amended. A fewe daies after this ouerthrowe, the Lord of <hi>Villeroy</hi> one of the chiefe of the contrarie faction, ſéeming deſirous to reclaime himſelfe, and to prouide for his particular ſafetie, drewe néere to <hi>Mant,</hi> where through his maieſties permiſſion he had ſome communication with <hi>Monſieur du Pleſſis Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay,</hi> who for his part vſed him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch fauorable ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches concerning not onely his own particular cauſe, but alſo the generall, that he fained himſelfe willing to enterpriſe ſome treatie of peace. Afterward he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned openly while the ſiege laie about <hi>Melune,</hi> and albeit his maieſtie were aduertiſed that this his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation was nothing but deceit: alſo that the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour might bee firſt deceiued, yet with this onelie confidence, that with his ſole diſcretion and franchize he might conuert them from their bad purpoſes into contrarie reſolutions, as many times it hath fallen out, that ſet conſpiracies haue ben confounded by the innocent preſence of thoſe againſt whom they ſhould haue bene put in execution, he forbare not to receiue him with as great humanitie, as if he had bene aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that his Commiſſion imported as good purpoſes, as he was certaine of the contrarie, whereby the ſaid Lord of <hi>Villeroy</hi> found himſelfe ſo ſurprized, that hée did halfe confeſſe this his conuerſion, and proteſted that hee woulde more faithfully emploie himſelfe thereabouts then before hee had done. In the meane time his Maieſtie hauing in a ſhort ſpace recouered all that laie vpon the riuers of <hi>Sein, Marne, Yonne,</hi> and <hi>Oyſe,</hi> he determined to drawe néere vnto the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Paris</hi> (in purpoſe to recouer it, and to roote out the rebellion in the ſame place where it firſt began, yet with a milde and naturall death deuoide of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, terror or conuulſion) which he found ſo weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended, that he might haue carried it with as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12964:3"/> ſmall labour as anie of the leaſt towns in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: which his abilitie continued the ſpace of foure moneths that he enuironed it, yea it not onely ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, but became daily more eaſie in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were within, had towarde the end loſt three parts of their men of ſeruice, and his maieſties armie was ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened and augmented the one halfe: howbeit ſo oft as it came to deliberation, (as there might be diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of Councels) his maieſtie conſidering that <hi>Paris</hi> was the head Citie and principall ornament of his Realme: that therein remained ſo many Princeſſes that were allied vnto him, ſo many good and ancient families, ſo many Churches and religious houſes, with perſons appertaining to the ſeruice of the ſame, who for the moſt part peraduenture were innocent of this rebellion, and yet the ſaid towne being taken by force, could not be exempt or fréed from ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and violence as in ſo furious an accident can no waie be eſchued, could neuer bee induced to conſent to that reſolution before he had attempted all other meanes: yea hardly would he grant to take the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbes, not as a matter vnneceſſarie to be done, but for feare leaſt the one might draw on the other: Alſo that the ſouldiers ſéeing themſelues ſo néere to ſo good a bootie, ſhould haue ben hardly reſtrained from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding farther, as in déed it was the greateſt labour that the king and the chiefeſt of his Captaines had during the whole ſiege, to reſtraine their ſouldiours from anie farther enterpriſe: for there was no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be made betwéene the attempting to execute it and the taking of the ſuburbes, which was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at once without anie reſiſtance. Alſo that which ſince hath bene ſéene, albeit repugnant to rule, viz. that the leſſe containeth not the greater, yet ſeuen or eight thouſand ſouldiers that lodged in the ſuburbs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12964:4"/> kept incloſed aboue thirty thouſand armed men that were in the ſayd towne, ought to be proofe ſufficient, that the taking thereof perforce could not haue béene auoided.</p>
            <p>Herevpon his Maieſtie, to the end not to loſe the ſaid town, but to preſerue the honor of ſo many fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and to ſpare the ſhedding of ſuch innocent blood as might haue bin ſpilt, reſolued to tame them with want of foode, and rather with patience to beare out the delay of whatſoeuer ſiege, then to practiſe any farther indeuour: wherein he had two purpoſes, either that it would fall out through the ſaid ſiege, that vpon the ſaid want, they that were within ſhould not be able to hold out, or elſe that the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> would approch to their ſuccour, whereby he might haue oportunitie to fight with him, which was the thing that he moſt deſired, as ſéeking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by rather to plucke vp the roote of the miſchiefe, then to cut off the branches. And had his maieſtie béene as reſolute and implacable in the firſt, as he hath ſhewed himſelfe moſt carefull in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond, the towne had vndoubtedly bene his. Indéede the reaſon of war willeth that being once reſolued to fight and conquer the obſtinacie of the beſieged with faſting and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, we ſhould not ſuffer any victuals whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer to be brought in by any whomſoeuer, alſo that we ſhould ſhut in al that were within and not ſuffer any, ſo much as one, to come forth, to the end that the more there were within, the ſooner the victuals might be conſumed: and this rule ought to haue bin obſerued with all ſeueritie and without fauour or exception. Yet during the laſt moneth of the ſiege that want and miſerie within the towne were ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme, the cries ſo fearefull of ſuch numbers as day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dyed in the ſtréetes for hunger, &amp; of ſo many others,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12964:4"/> whoſe rage was ſuch that openly they eate the dogs raw: the houlings of the people, the lamentations of ſuch mothers as miſſed their children, did pearce not onely the aire but the ſtone wals, ſo as his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie could not abide to heare them with ſuch beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſtinacie, as they that were the cauſers did ſée them with their eyes: yea thoſe that had yet ſome prouiſion of victuals accounted all this people but vnprofitable ſoules, and thought long to haue them all dead and caſt away, ſo that as the kings courage and magnanimitie are inuincible, ſo were his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie and clemencie eaſie to be ouercome and did ſoone ſtoope to theſe monſtrous pities, chooſing rather to erre in the rules of warre than of nature, euen of his owne nature which aboundeth in mildneſſe and clemencie. He conſidered that all this people were Chriſtians, that they were his ſubiectes, that the moſt part were peraduenture innocent, &amp; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was requiſite to releaſe them from this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire wherein they were loſt, and in the end his good nature brake all barres of the lawes of warre. Firſt he granted a Paſſeport for all the women, maidens, and children, and for all the Schollers that were willing to come forth: afterward he extended it to religious perſons and Church men: And finally he enlarged it to thoſe that had bene his greateſt eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, yea he tooke care that at their comming forth they might be curteouſly receiued throughout all his Townes, whither they liſt to repaire. He ſuffered the Princes and Princeſſes that were in the Towne to be relieued with ſome proportion of victuals, which ſince hath bene but badly conſidered: ſo that it may be confeſſed that the ſiege continued longer by one moneth than it ſhould, and ſo conſequently had not the due effect: howbeit, ſith this is the cauſe, it is ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12964:5"/> holy and agréeable vnto God, that certainly it ſhall be rewarded double, and will be worth the recouerie not onely of <hi>Paris,</hi> but of the whole eſtate or more, ſo infinite are Gods graces and heauenly rewards.</p>
            <p>Moreouer his maieſtie in all theſe extremities ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer failed in al fatherly dueties that might be, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them by publike letters and meſſengers to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, with aſſurance of all things concerning Catholike Religion, &amp; whatſoeuer other good vſage &amp; quiet peace. He permitted the Cardinall of <hi>Gondy</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Lions</hi> to haue recourſe from them vnto him, who departed again ſo well ſatiſfied and contented, that they wept to conſider how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did erre in an opinion that they had conceiued of his maieſtie, farre other then they ought to haue: He alſo gaue them leaue to paſſe to the Duke of <hi>Maine,</hi> yet did all theſe his curteſies turne to poiſon and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim in their corrupted ſtomakes: whereof appeared a moſt certaine, but ſhamefull proofe, in that when the ſaid Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> returned the ſaid Cardinall of <hi>Gondy</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Lions</hi> vnto his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, with proteſtation that he deſired nothing ſo much as peace. He wrote likewiſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame time to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pariſians by one of his Secretaries that followed their traine, that they ſhould not be diſmayd for this Parley, and that he would rather dye then conclude any peace: which letter falling from him that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it, and being ſhewed to the ſaid Duke of <hi>Mayne,</hi> he could not denie the ſigning thereof: which when the Archbiſhop of <hi>Lions</hi> obiected vnto him, he had no other excuſe but that he was ſurpriſed: yet might he more truely haue ſaid that thereby he purpoſed to haue ſurpriſed as well the one as the other.</p>
            <p>If his maieſtie hath bene ſomewhat tender, and not altogither ſo ſtrict as the lawes of war do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12964:5"/> in ſuch rigor as was to be practiſed againſt the Pariſians, he hath ſufficiently recompenced the ſame in his care and diligence to méete with his enimies in the fielde, which hath alwayes bene his greateſt deſire, rather then with the Cannon to beat his townes and the poore inhabitants of the ſame. Immediatly after the beginning of the ſiege the King being aduertiſed that the Duke of <hi>Mayne,</hi> at his returne out of Flanders, whither he went to craue ſuccour of the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> hauing alreadie gathered ſome troopes, was departed with <hi>Balagny</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Paul</hi> to march and approch toward <hi>Paris,</hi> went from his armie with a troope of Horſemen without any baggage, and marched ſeuentéene leagues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a baite to méete with him, and came ſhort but one houre, hauing forced him to ſhut vp himſelfe in the towne of <hi>Laon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After that the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> hauing gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red great ſuccour and being come to <hi>Meaux,</hi> ſtill gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing out that he came to giue battaile, his ſaid maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie departed againe from his armie with a troupe of horſe, and came to méet him almoſt to <hi>Meaux,</hi> where he found him encloſed betwéene the riuer of <hi>Marne,</hi> and that which commeth from <hi>Grecy,</hi> as fearing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be beſieged, than indeuoring to beſiege others, &amp; this he did expecting the comming of the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> at whoſe arriuall and the daie following, they publiſhed euery where that they wold giue bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, whereat his maieſtie reioyced more than at anie other thing. And in deede the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> beeing come and ioyned with the ſaid Duke of <hi>Maine,</hi> they began within two daies after to march, and paſſed the brooke that runneth by the towne of <hi>Claye,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Freſne</hi> where they lodged, ſo that his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hoping the next daie to haue battaile, hauing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12964:6"/> commended himſelfe to God (as in all ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he there beginneth) and exhorted euerie one to do the like, he departed from the Village of <hi>Challiot</hi> neere to <hi>Paris</hi> vpon Wedneſday the nine and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith of the laſt moneth, and appointed the generall méeting of his whole army the next day in the plaine of <hi>Bondy,</hi> which lieth vpon the head of the foreſt of <hi>Eurie</hi> which was the direct way for the enimie, and to the end alſo to be ready to méete them if they tooke the way on the ſide whereby to ſhunne the paſſage thorough the ſaid foreſt: hauing alſo the ſame day brought his footemen that lay in the ſuburbes of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> to be at the battaile, the armie all the while ſtood vpon the ſaid plaine of <hi>Bondie</hi> in battaile array, but had no newes of the enimie. Thither did his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie cauſe his power to come and ſtay two dayes, where there appeared no enimy in any corner. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he reſolued vpon Friday to draw nearer to them and to lodge at <hi>Chelles,</hi> to which end hauing ſent the Lord of <hi>Lauerdin</hi> one of the marſhals of his campe, and the Lord of <hi>Chaſtillion:</hi> at their arriuall they found the enimies marſhals and harbingers that had begunne to prouide the lodgings, whom they droue away: and his maieſtie comming ſoone after, deſcried ſome ſeuen or eight hundred of the enimies Horſe, among whom the two Generals were ſaid to be, whom he charged with a farre leſſe number, and followed beating of them euen to their lodgings. Vpon Saturday the firſt of this moneth, his highnes ſtood aſſured of battaile aboue the ſaid village of <hi>Chelles,</hi> which was a plaine that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde it two ſmall hilles, at the head deuided from a ſmal wood with a brooke, and in the ſaid wood is a Caſtle called <hi>Brou,</hi> and beyond it a moore ſeparate from a little plaine that lieth betwéene the ſaid caſtle
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12964:6"/> and the moore, with an other ſmall brooke, which was the lodging that the enimie had taken. His ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties armie ſtoode in battaile aray: About eleuen of the clocke the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> got vnto one of the hilles, to the end to view it, and hauing ſéene it, it is ſaid he fetched as great a ſigh as if it ſhould haue bene his laſt: and turning to the Duked of <hi>Mayne,</hi> did greatly reproch him, ſaying, that this was not the armie of tenne thouſand men, that he had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to fight withall, but that he there deſcried aboue fiue and twentie thouſand, the beſt in order that euer he had ſéene. This aſtoniſhment is not to bo obiected vnto him as a fault: for here had bene matter to haue daunted one that had both ſéene and lead greater armies than he, as indéed it may be truely ſaid to haue bene the braueſt armie that had bene ſéene in France a long time. It contained at the leaſt eightéene thouſand footemen, whereof ſixe thouſand were ſtrangers, and fiue or ſixe thouſand Horſes, of whom almoſt foure thouſand were french Gentlemen, and of the beſt houſes in France. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were ſixe Princes, two Maſhals of France, and more Captaines and leaders of armies then are in all the reſt of Chriſtendome. The Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> in liew of comming to battaile, changed all his mens weapons, and for ſpeares furniſhed them with Mattockes and Shouels, wherewith all the night they entrenched themſelues within the moore, wherein both the Horſemen and footmen were lodged.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Saterday after dinner his maieſtie draue them from the brooke, the wood and the houſe that ſtood in the wood, ſo that they retired into the ſaid moore, and from thence forth the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> in liew of battaile, ſought onely to intrench &amp; fortifie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12964:7"/> himſelfe, which he did verie ſtrongly. At night his maieſtie returned to lodge at the ſaide village of <hi>Chelles.</hi> Euerie daie after he laboured by al meanes to drawe them to the battell, cauſing continual ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, wherein ſtill ſome of their men ſtayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, all which notwithſtanding there was no meanes to prouoke them anie farther, openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing that vppon the ſaturdaie at afternoone they loſt all ſtomacke to battell. Within a few dayes after they determined to aſſaile the little towne of <hi>Laigny</hi> that was within halfe a league behind them, &amp; hauing made a bridge of Boates almoſt hard by the towne, vpon the eight day by breake of day, they paſſed ouer the moſt part of their footemen, beating it from ouer the riuer with nine péeces, the breach was made before his highneſſe had in manner anie notice thereof, by reaſon the winde was ſo turned, and the miſt ſo great and thick that the Canon could not be heard. There was in it ſome two or thrée hundred men, who defended it ſo well, that the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my loſt the greater number, and had the ſuccour that was ſent come neuer ſo little ſooner, they had not ſo eaſily carried it awaie.</p>
            <p>It appeared well that there was neuer a village in France better able to defend it ſelfe, conſidering that they neuer forced it vpon any other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but cauſed it to be diſmantelled ſo ſoone as they had taken it. His maieſty imagining that this might haue chéered vp their courage, commanded the ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh the next day hotter then before, wherewith they were the leſſe prouoked. Finally, conſidering that the moſt part of this gentrie, who at the onely report of this battaile were come in without any furniture, knowing themſelues out of hope thereof, did vrge their departure. He thought it time to think
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12964:7"/> vpon ſome other kind of warre againſt the enimie, then to linger vpon drawing them to a generall fight, whereof they had ſufficiently ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnwilling to taſt: yet before he would enter into this determination he purpoſed to trie one meanes more to draw them thereto. Wherefore he determined to make ſhew as if he would force <hi>Paris,</hi> and to the ſame end departed the tenth day at night from <hi>Chelles</hi> with a good troope of footemen and ſome gentrie, ſo to get by the breake of day to the gates of <hi>Paris</hi> and to offer the aſſault, hauing with all giuen commandement that the armie ſhould the next morning depart and returne to <hi>Bondy:</hi> And this he did with this intent, that the enimie knowing of his returne to <hi>Paris</hi> ſhould follow his armie, which might be an occaſion of battaile: But the enterpriſe of <hi>Paris</hi> being diſcouered had no ſucceſſe, as alſo had not the other: for all this notwithſtanding, the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie durſt not come forth of his moore, as ſtanding in continuall feare of ſome falſe baite whereby to draw them where they were not reſolued to come: which by this occaſion rather then any other, was fully confirmed, becauſe that ſeing his maieſties for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeparate they ſtirred not, as alſo that now there was no hope of any other than ſuch as leaſure might afford.</p>
            <p>This was the cauſe why his maieſtie being retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his armie at the ſaid place of <hi>Bondy,</hi> where al the day it had waited for the enimies approch, and hearing no newes of their diſlodging, determined the ſame day to take vp his lodging at <hi>Goneſſe.</hi> The next morning hauing aſſembled the Princes, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the crowne, and other great Captaines pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the ſaid armie, it was among them thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſed and debated, that it was euident and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12964:8"/> plaine that the Prince of Parmas intent was not for to fight: that to hope to force him therto in time by lodging ſtill neere vnto him, he ſhould haue the aduantage of them, his armie beeing freſh and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paie, conſiſting of ſtrangers, who doe not light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcatter, where contrariwiſe his maieſties for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were for the moſt part tired, expecting no paie: That to returne to the ſiege of Paris, ſith his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie was not minded to take it perforce, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to exſpect their laſt extremitie, the time wold be ouer long, the rather becauſe they hauing had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie toward the parties of Beauſſe, euer ſince the departure of the army toward Chelles, might haue ſufficiently refurniſhed themſelues for the time. That ſith the enemie would not warre after our manner, it was meete we ſhould applie our ſelues to his: and ſith hee woulde not haue the honour to fight with ſo many honorable perſonages, as to that end were aſſembled, it was requiſite to fight and diſtreſſe him with the want of victualles and other ſuch diſcommodities. That his maieſtie furniſhing his townes that lie vpon the riuer of Seine with victualls and ſtrong garriſons, ſhoulde ſtill keepe Paris as ſtraightly beſieged, as with the preſence of an armie, &amp; therefore that he ſhould not neede ſo ſtrong a one therabout as his was. That it might ſuffice to haue a meane power wherwith ſo ofte as the enemie ſhould attempt any thing, ſtill be at his héeles. That returning his forces into their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces from whence they came, woulde be a greate reliefe to the ſayd prouinces, and by refreſhing his ſayd troupes, he ſhould ſtil yeld them opportunitie to get ſomewhat. That when the forrein forces ſhal chance to enter, vpon the returne of his troups thus refreſhed, and their ioyning with him, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie ſhall finde himſelfe twice as ſtronge as hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12964:8"/> now is, and withall, ſhall ſo bridel the enemies, as they may not performe any great exploite: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, the others comming vppon them, it will be a meanes to force them farther then to entrench in the moore. This opinion, with ſundrie good and ſufficient reaſons being beſt liked, his maieſtie in this famous councell concluded and decréed to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the ſayd propoſition, purpoſing to begin with the towne of Saint Denis, for the defence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ſtroue who ſhould get the charge, euerie one hoping that therein reſted ſome honour to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed. In the end it fel to the Lord of Lauerdin, who tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfully accepted it. He prouided alſo ſtrong garriſons to fortifie the townes of Melune, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beile, Senlis, Meulan, Maunt, and ſundrie others, of which the leaſt might ſuffice to bring the ſayde Duke of Parmas power on their knées. His maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie alſo reſolued to returne into Touraine, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iou and Maine, the Lorde Prince of Contie, into Normandie the Duke of Montpenfier, into Picar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the D. of Longueuil, into Champaigne the D. of Neuers, &amp; into Burgondie the Marſhall Aumont, euerie of them with good forces ſufficient to keepe the ſaid prouinces in peace.</p>
            <p>He alſo retained ſtill about himſelfe a meane power, yet ſtrong and mighty enough to make head againſt the enemie, and to keepe him from anie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, before he would be at their elbowes: withall purpoſing to holde them ſo ſhort, that in a ſmall time he might ſtill be with them as occaſion might require. This forme of warre did he iudge, (conſidering that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies reſolution tended not to fight) to bee more to their diſcommoditie and hinderance than anie other. Whereupon as the Lordes of Guich, Ragnie, &amp; Ciper were vpon their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12964:9"/> retreat, not hauing aboue ſixe ſcore fighting men, they met with the Vicount <hi>Tauannes</hi> retiring into <hi>Normandie</hi> with about fiue hundred Horſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of aboue halfe were <hi>Cuiraſſes</hi> and the reſt Harcubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziers, whom in the end they charged and ouerthrew néere to <hi>Meulay,</hi> leauing of them aboue fiftie deade in the place, and taking as many priſoners togither with all their baggage.</p>
            <p>This is the true Hiſtorie of all that hath paſſed in his maieſties armie ſince the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> ioyned with his enimies. Alſo the principall reaſons that moued him to reſolue vpon the diſſoluing of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whereof he wiſheth by theſe remembrances all his Gouernors and Lieutenants general of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, his courtes of parliament, his Nobilitie, his townes and all other his officers to be informed, that they may certifie all other his good and faithfull ſubiects, to the end they may know that this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not ſleightly taken, neither by force nor compulſion, but vpon ripe deliberation and milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie diſcretion, with the aduice and conſent of the greateſt and wiſeſt Captaines at this daie in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, who ſtill are aſſiſtant vnto the King, alſo that of the ſaid reſolution there is no other to be expected but all good ſucceſſe: that God himſelfe hath ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly dealt in the matter, alwaies ſhewing that he hath taken this ſo iuſt a cauſe into his protection, as not permitting ſo many Princes, ſo many great Lords and wiſe Captaines, euen ſufficient to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to this crowne thrée or foure others, to hazarde themſelues in battell againſt thoſe ſtrangers, who all for the moſt part are mercinarie men, ſo as their whole loſſe is not to counteruaile the leaſt of a hundred Princes and Lordes which might haue bene caſt awaie.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12964:9"/>
            <p>It doth alſo euidently appeare, that he déemeth them vnworthie to be fought withall in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and is determined to bring them to deſtruction with leſſe honour, and to ouerthrowe and defeate them by two inward enemies whome they haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, namely, want of victualles, which doth alreadie pinch them extremely, and diuiſion, which likewiſe is growen ſo great, that the French not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble anie longer to beare the Spaniards inſolencie, are for the moſt part retired: &amp; there is no more in this armie of ſtrangers, but the duke of <hi>Maine</hi> and ſome ſmal number of French men, whom they lead about as it were in triumph. For others haue they not yet gotten, as not hauing offered one ſole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, and in ſuch as haue bene preſented them, ſtill going awaie with loſſe. They haue not as yet reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the Ancients which they loſt at <hi>Eurie,</hi> neither anie other wherewith to get them againe by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. The Pariſians cannot boaſt their frantike obſtinacie to be conſtancie, but are rather to confes that it is Gods ſufferance, to the end to driue them to a longer penance, as alſo to be themſelues the execucioners of the firſt puniſhments that he hath decréed againſt them: and for the ſecond, hauing this comfort and recompence for their pacience and great ſeruice done to the Duke of <hi>Maine,</hi> viz. to ſée the <hi>Spaniards</hi> whom he hath brought euen home vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, become maſters of themſelues and of their houſes, their wiues and their daughters, wherein they may now he an example to others that ſhould haue ſerued them in the preuention of the miſchief that both doth and ſtill wil oppreſſe them, vntill it may pleaſe God to ſuffer his Maieſtie to be their deliuerer.</p>
            <p>Now hath the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> good cauſe to féele
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12964:10"/> and iudge that his treacle is worſe then the poiſon, and that the remedie which himſelfe hath ſought, is farre more dangerous than the miſchiefe that he went about to cure. Neither ſhal the king of Spaine be quite fruſtrate of the reward to him promiſed by this trouble which he vpholdeth and nouriſheth in this realme, by cloking his ambition with the falſe pretence of religion, which he ought firſt to haue pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed at his owne home, by rooting out paganiſme, which is ſo ordinarie and whereof he reapeth profite and reuenue, permitting in <hi>Granado, Andalouzia</hi> and <hi>Arragon,</hi> more villages without Chriſtians, than he hath good Chriſtians in his beſt townes. It is Gods will that he ſhould liue, to the end in his old dayes to lay vpon him the deſerued iudgement of ſuch ſacriledge as himſelfe committeth, enfringinge the confederacies that he hath with this crowne, which are not written in paper or parchment onely, but alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> memories of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as kiſſes &amp; publik faith. The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> who had ſo wiſely foreſéene the reaſon why they ſought to make him vndertake the enterpriſe of England, hath failed in this, wherein he ſhall ſhortly know that he ſhall haue more time to repent, then meanes of remedie. Al the miſchiefe that this hath wrought, is that it hath ſo much the longer delayed the effect of his maieſties good meanings, who could not by reaſon of ſuch great and continual affaires as haue ſtill followed him, hitherto put in effect the afore reſolued conuocation of the chiefe of this realme, with whom déepely to haue conſidered of whatſoeuer may be neceſſarie to the wealth and peace therof, which he claimeth as his owne, the one being inſeparable from the other: As alſo he could get no leaſure to take counſaile, firſt with God and then with men, by whom he might haue bene aſſiſted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12964:10"/> and holpen to reſolue vpon whatſoeuer his good and affectionate catholike ſubiects do deſire at his hands. It is greatly to be hoped that by this <hi>Criſis</hi> God wil at this time cure the diſeaſe, and therefore it is al our parts with one minde to cal vpon him, and to intreat him to grant vs his grace, wherewith the helpe of men ſhal not faile. The nobilitie hath ſufficiently in all occaſions y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue bin offered, giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their good mindes to ſacrifice their liues for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deliuerie of their king and realme from this canker of rebellion. Alſo it muſt follow that France muſt abandon &amp; giue ouer the french name and language, if at this time ſhe frée not her ſelfe from ſo many pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie tyrants as do now oppreſſe her, and are determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to rent and ſhare her among them: his Maieſtie proteſteth before God, that he wil neuer leaue armes vntill this be performed, and is reſolued therein to imploy the reſt of his life, if neceſſitie ſo require, as alſo he adiureth all the Princes, officers of the crowne, courtes of Parliament and all other orders of this eſtate, neuer to reſt themſelues, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe earneſtly to take courage againſt the ſtorme, to the end they might guide this veſſell to the hauen of health, where we ſée our God ſtretching forth his arme vnto vs, aſſuring them that vpon the preſent ariuall therof, he wil imploy his whole &amp; firſt leaſure on the granting to his ſubiects whatſoeuer conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation he may, and that God ſhal more particularly inſpire him withall, from whom he craueth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his poore people all peace and reliefe poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wiſhing no longer life then during the ſame to haue meanes to purchaſe vnto them that benifite, which is the whole fruit and reward that he deſireth for his labours.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
